<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Students | SciRuby]]></title>
  <link href="http://sciruby.com/blog/categories/students/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://sciruby.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-19T16:47:34-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://sciruby.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[SciRuby]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction to the Minimization and Integration project (Rajat)]]></title>
    <link href="http://sciruby.com/blog/2014/06/04/introduction-to-the-minimization-and-integration-project/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-04T14:23:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://sciruby.com/blog/2014/06/04/introduction-to-the-minimization-and-integration-project</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="note"><strong>Editor's Note:</strong> We have two students
working on numerical minimization and integration this summer, Rajat and
Lahiru. Lahiru will be writing a separate post about his work.</p>


<h2>Introduction to the Minimization and Integration Project</h2>

<p>Hi. My name is Rajat Kapoor and I have been selected to work with
SciRuby for Google Summer of Code 2014.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/minimization">Minimization</a> and
<a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/integration">Integration</a> are two of the
many available gems in the SciRuby suite. My project this year aims to
improve these gems to replicate the functionality provided by GNU's
GSL. I will be trying to implement all the minimization and
integration algorithms present in GSL in pure Ruby, with improvements
as needed, so that these functions are easily accesible to all Ruby
users, while the users which have GSL already installed will have an
advantage in terms of speedy computations.</p>

<h2>What Minimization and Integration actually mean</h2>

<p>Minimization refers to the process of finding out the minimum of a
mathematical function whose values might depend on multiple
variables. Unidimensional minimization restricts these problems to
functions of one single variable. Integration is the same as the very
widely used concept in calculus which basically boils down to finding
the summation of the value of a function at small intervals, when the
width of the intervals in infinitesimally small. I can bet that you
knowingly or unknowingly use both these things on a daily basis.</p>

<h2>The plan</h2>

<p>The project can be broken into two major parts: Minimization and
Integration, as these are two seperate gems.</p>

<p>The Minimization gem can be broken in two parts: unidimensional (or
univariate) and multidimensional (multivariate). With respect to
coding, these two can again be broken down into sub-parts: pure Ruby
implementations and GSL support. The Integration gem will include
the pure Ruby implementations as well as GSL support. Along with this,
some support for symbolic integration will be added for JRuby
users by way of the JScience library.</p>

<h2>Progress</h2>

<p>The pure Ruby implementations of the unidimensional minimization part
are almost finished. I am also working on the GSL support for the same
along with it. I plan to finish up any unidimensional minimization
work by the end of this week and start the work with multidimensional
minimization methods.</p>

<p>Keep watching this blog for more updates regarding my project.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing the FFTW SciRuby GSoC project]]></title>
    <link href="http://sciruby.com/blog/2014/06/04/introducing-the-fftw-sciruby-gsoc-project/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-04T12:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://sciruby.com/blog/2014/06/04/introducing-the-fftw-sciruby-gsoc-project</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My name is Magdalen Berns and I am a physics student with a technical
background in live audio. I am particularly interested in using science
and technology to improve access for all.</p>

<p>This summer, I will be working on implementing the external library
appropriately named "Fastest Fourier Transform in the West" version 3
(FFTW3) C and Fortran API in Ruby for this year's Google Summer of Code
(GSoC).</p>

<p>The primary aim of the project is to give SciRuby the capability to
handle signal analysis, processing and synthesis by performing discrete
fast Fourier transform operations on NMatrix objects.</p>

<p>After some investigation during the preparation stages of GSoC, it was
determined that implementing FFTW3 is more desirable than starting from
scratch in pure Ruby because the FFTW3 API is already extensively used,
developed, and optimised far beyond what would be achievable in just
three months. So, putting FFTW3 in the driving seat allows the SciRuby
project to take advantage of the good work of the FFTW3 developers by
bringing it to Ruby.</p>

<p>Putting NMatrix to the test with FFTW3 should give users the
opportunity to test drive NMatrix &mdash; and SciRuby's NMatrix developers a
chance to root out bugs.</p>

<p>Since a gem called ruby-fftw3 already existed to perform FFTW3 operations
on NArray objects, I forked that repository as a starting point. <a href="https://github.com/thisMagpie/fftw">Things are progressing on my Github fork</a> right now.</p>

<p>My mentor for this project is Colin Fuller who is an exceptionally
talented programmer &mdash; and he really knows his git too. He has been a
great help as I adapt to the learning curve of working in C and
Ruby (languages which I am less familiar with than say, Java or
JavaScript).</p>

<p>As I work, I intend to share useful gems of information I gather. Those, in addition to my weekly project updates, will appear right here in this blog so others can hopefully benefit.</p>

<p>I have already posted a few useful bits and bobs on
<a href="http://thismagpie.com">thismagpie.com</a> which relate to my work so far.
I hope to add those to the SciRuby blog, too, provided
the readers are interested in that and time permits. Of course, readers here can feel free to have a browse
of the keywords <a href="http://thismagpie.com/keyword/sciruby">sciruby</a>,
<a href="http://thismagpie.com/keyword/ruby">ruby</a> and
<a href="http://thismagpie.com/keyword/git">git</a> on there for the time being.
I sometimes add posts, manuals and tutorials from external sites where I
find useful ones on the web too, so watch out for these too.</p>

<p>Please, feel free to watch or follow along as the project comes together
and those inclined are welcome to share constructive comments and advice
or raise bugs on the fftw3 issue tracker. Input about my work is very
welcome as the project progresses. This gem is being written for the
community, after all!</p>

<p>You can find me on Twitter (Facebook) or GitHub under the username @thisMagpie.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing the GSoC 2014 D3 Project]]></title>
    <link href="http://sciruby.com/blog/2014/06/02/introducing-gsoc-2014-the-d3-project/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-02T14:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://sciruby.com/blog/2014/06/02/introducing-gsoc-2014-the-d3-project</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello. I am Naoki, one of four Google Summer of Code (GSoC) 2014
students in SciRuby. Let me introduce my project. The goal of the GSoC
2014 D3 Project is to create a new plotting library for
SciRuby. <a href="http://d3js.org/">D3.js</a> is the most suitable JavaScript
library to achieve this goal.</p>

<p>There are several non-Ruby plotting software libraries in the wild,
like ggplot, matplotlib, and ggplot2. Actually, SciRuby already has
its own plotting libraries named
<a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/plotrb">Plotrb</a> and
<a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/rubyvis">Rubyvis</a>. The main feature of my
project compared with those software packages is <em>interactivity</em>.
Interactivity has various meanings here: interactivity when generating
plots, interactivity when viewing them, and server&ndash;client
interactivity. My project includes all of those.</p>

<p>My project can be divided into two components, one JavaScript and the
other Ruby. JavaScript serves as a back-end, and Ruby as a
front-end. I'm currently working on the former part. Have a look at a
few examples I've assembled:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://bl.ocks.org/domitry/b8785f02f36deef567ce">Multiple panes</a></li>
<li><a href="http://bl.ocks.org/domitry/2f53781449025f772676">Bar chart</a></li>
<li><a href="http://bl.ocks.org/domitry/e9a914b78f3a576ed3bb">Line</a></li>
<li><a href="http://bl.ocks.org/domitry/308e27d8d12c1374e61f">Scatter</a></li>
<li><a href="http://bl.ocks.org/domitry/f215d5ff3bd3f5fec2ad">Another theme</a></li>
</ul>


<p>This project involves a number of challenges, but I believe it to be
achievable during this Summer of Code. Thank you for reading!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to use NMatrix's shortcuts]]></title>
    <link href="http://sciruby.com/blog/2012/12/07/how-to-use-nmatrix-shortcuts/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-07T12:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://sciruby.com/blog/2012/12/07/how-to-use-nmatrix-shortcuts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="warning"><strong>Warning:</strong> This code predates v0.0.9 alpha, which is when the NMatrix constructor changed. Please check the <a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/nmatrix/wiki/Getting-started#shortcuts">NMatrix Getting Started guide</a> for the most recent information.</p>


<p>John Woods <a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/nmatrix/commit/2b480ce0985affc7218fc341fcb4e5024b30545b">merged my last pull request to NMatrix</a> recently and I wanted to write about why we created these shortcuts and what can be done with them. <!--more--></p>

<h2>The need for shortcuts</h2>

<p>The first iteration of NMatrix shortcuts was written by <a href="https://github.com/dcarrera">Daniel Carrera</a> and sent to the mailing list, where I started working with them. Some discussions, decisions and two pull requests later, we have a working set of methods to create common matrices (<code>zeros</code>, <code>ones</code>, <code>random</code>, etc) and do some cool stuff (<code>column</code> and <code>linspace</code>) very easily.</p>

<p>There are at least two good reasons to have these shortcuts: MATLAB users are going to feel at home, and the shortcuts allow us to prototype and experiment more rapidly. For example, it's dead simple to create an identify matrix when you need one:</p>

<pre><code>&gt;&gt; require 'nmatrix'

&gt;&gt; matrix = NMatrix.identity(3) # 3x3
=&gt; #&lt;NMatrix:0x007faa5b8cda40shape:[3,3] dtype:float64 stype:dense&gt; 
&gt;&gt; matrix.pp

# [1.0, 0.0, 0.0]
# [0.0, 1.0, 0.0]
# [0.0, 0.0, 1.0]
</code></pre>

<p>And a random matrix to test some operation:</p>

<pre><code>&gt;&gt; rand_matrix = NMatrix.random(4) # 4x4
=&gt; #&lt;NMatrix:0x007faa5b01cdd8shape:[4,4] dtype:float64 stype:dense&gt;
&gt;&gt; rand_matrix.pp

# [0.5933103148378577, 0.8556103970281977, 0.7176768395610358, 0.07160353964395305]
# [0.8566365570076784, 0.33925854948960343, 0.5994298479703805, 0.6906794137948586]
# [0.5684593743073485, 0.10273166792035393, 0.46187577773882293, 0.586085963973687]
# [0.8944982538369494, 0.9896291945923837, 0.8787034784673503, 0.5933103148378577]
</code></pre>

<h2>Shortcuts available</h2>

<p>The following list is taken from <a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/nmatrix/wiki/NMatrix">NMatrix's wiki</a>. All are class methods on <code>NMatrix</code>.</p>

<pre><code>ones(3,3)                    # A 3x3 matrix of ones.
zeros(4,4) or zeroes(4,4)    # Creates a matrix of zeros with dimensions as parameters.
identity(5,5) or eye(5,5)    # A 5x5 identity matrix. Only works with NMatrix.
seq(8)                       # An 8-vector with a sequence of values from 0 to 7.
random(6,6)                  # A 6x6 matrix of random values between 0 and 1.

column(2)                    # Return the 2nd column of the original matrix. Only works with NMatrix.

indgen(8)                    # To make IDL users happy. Same as `seq(8, :int32)`.
findgen(8)                   # Same as `seq(8, :float32)`.
bindgen(8)                   # Same as `seq(8, :byte)`.
cindgen(8)                   # Same as `seq(8, :complex64)`.

linspace(0, pi, 100)         # A vector of 100 values from 0 to pi, inclusive. Only works with NVector.
</code></pre>

<p>The method names are mostly from MATLAB. In the future, when more functionality is added, we'll try to create a more "Ruby-like" feel to the API. But as these shortcuts do very primitive tasks, there isn't any obvious room for improvement. (Feel free to prove us wrong, however!)</p>

<p>I'll create a separate wiki page for the shortcuts to be able to organize and put more information about how to use them. But I want to create a better RDoc documentation for NMatrix — so the full API will probably be referenced there. I'll write a new blog post here when something along these lines is done.</p>

<h2>Examples</h2>

<p>First, let's try normalizing the columns of an NMatrix.</p>

<pre><code>require 'nmatrix'

m = NMatrix.seq(3, :float32)
m.pp

# [0.0, 1.0, 2.0]
# [3.0, 4.0, 5.0]
# [6.0, 7.0, 8.0]

(0 .. m.shape[1] - 1).each do |j|
  col = m.column(j)
    norm = Math.sqrt(col.transpose.dot(col)[0, 0])
    (0 .. m.shape[0] - 1).each { |i| m[i,j] /= norm }
end

m.pp

# [0.0, 0.12309148907661438, 0.20739033818244934]
# [0.4472135901451111, 0.4923659563064575, 0.5184758305549622]
# [0.8944271802902222, 0.861640453338623, 0.8295613527297974]

(0 .. m.shape[1] - 1).each do |j|
  col = m.column(j)
  puts Math.sqrt(col.transpose.dot(col)[0,0])
end

# 0.9999999701976772
# 1.0
# 1.0
</code></pre>

<p>Unfortunately, slice by reference isn't working on <code>HEAD</code>, or we could make a few additional improvements (see issue <a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/nmatrix/issues/51">#51</a>).</p>

<p>The other thing that I've wanted to do is to use <code>linspace</code> to generate points for plotting sines, cosines, etc. Here is an example:</p>

<pre><code>require 'nmatrix'

vector = NVector.linspace(0, Math::PI, 10)
vector.pretty_print

# 0.0
# 0.3490658503988659
# 0.6981317007977318
# 1.0471975511965976
# 1.3962634015954636
# 1.7453292519943295
# 2.0943951023931953
# 2.443460952792061
# 2.792526803190927
# 3.141592653589793

10.times do |i|
  vector[k, 0] = Math::sin(vector[k, 0])
end

vector.pretty_print

# 0.0
# 0.3420201433256687
# 0.6427876096865393
# 0.8660254037844386
# 0.984807753012208
# 0.984807753012208
# 0.8660254037844388
# 0.6427876096865395
# 0.3420201433256689
# 1.2246467991473532e-16
</code></pre>

<p>These results show a happy result, in that we are able to use NMatrix for simple tasks already. Of course, there are problems to be solved, e.g. slice by reference, inversion for all dtypes, eigenvalues. But it's going somewhere, it's growing.</p>

<p>I hope that by this time next year we'll have a very mature linear algebra library (and much more).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spring 2013 SciRuby Fellows Selected]]></title>
    <link href="http://sciruby.com/blog/2012/11/28/spring-2013-sciruby-fellows-selected/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-28T13:46:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://sciruby.com/blog/2012/11/28/spring-2013-sciruby-fellows-selected</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week we selected three excellent candidates for <a href="http://sciruby.com/blog/2012/09/24/sciruby-receives-ruby-association-grant--fellowships-available/">SciRuby fellowships</a>. We were incredibly pleased to be able to offer so many fellowships, made possible in part by the generosity of an anonymous contributor. <!--more--></p>

<p><a href="http://github.com/agarie">Carlos Agarie</a> will be working half-time starting immediately on providing certain critical functionality to NMatrix and on improving our documentation. Specifically, matrix inversions and determinant calculations both depend upon BLAS, and in some cases CLAPACK. However, the CLAPACK interface is unavailable to most Mac users; and neither BLAS nor LAPACK provides rational support, which is on the NMatrix roadmap. Carlos is a Brazilian exchange student at Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University in Arizona.</p>

<p><a href="http://github.com/masaomi">Masaomi "Masa" Hatakeyama</a> is a post-doctoral researcher at the University of Zurich. He is devoting ten hours per week initially to adding NMatrix support to Ruby/GSL, while also improving the NMatrix unit tests. His work is critical to interoperability between NMatrix and the other SciRuby projects.</p>

<p>Finally, <a href="http://github.com/ryanmt">Ryan Taylor</a> is a biochemistry doctoral candidate at Brigham Young University in the United States. Ryan will be working full-time starting in January on NMatrix, and plans to contribute functionality essential to any matrix library---such as factorizations and decompositions; computations of trace, exponentials, square roots, norms, and tensors; basic statistics; transforms; and solvers.</p>

<p>We also want to take a moment to thank <a href="http://www.symora.com">Symora Networks</a> for its assistance. Specifically, the size of the Ruby Association grant is such that the U.S. requires us to apply for tax status, a somewhat expensive process for an open source project. Symora is providing the bulk of the money required for that application. Thanks also go to our many individual donors, who are just as necessary to this process.</p>

<p>And of course, none of this would be possible without the Ruby Association. They provided us not only with financial resources to grow our project, but also with an endorsement of our vision: Ruby needs scientific packages in order to grow as a language.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
